<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Revision$ -->
<chapter id="codecs">
<title>Codecs</title>

<para>
The <ulink url="../../codecs-status.html">codec status table</ulink> is a
complete list of all supported codecs, regenerated daily.
Some binary codecs for use with MPlayer are available in the
<ulink url="http://www.mplayerhq.hu/design7/dload.html#binary_codecs">download section</ulink>
of our homepage.
</para>

<para>
If you have a Win32 codec which is not supported yet, please read the
<ulink url="../../tech/win32-codec-howto">Win32 codec HOWTO</ulink>
and help us add support for it.
</para>


<!-- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -->


<sect1 id="audio-codecs">
<title>Audio codecs</title>


<sect2 id="swac3">
<title>Software AC-3 decoding</title>

<para>
This is the default decoder used for files with AC-3 audio.
</para>

<para>
The AC-3 decoder can create audio output mixes for 2, 4, or 6 speakers.
When configured for 6 speakers, this decoder provides separate output of
all the AC-3 channels to the sound driver, allowing for full "surround
sound" experience without the external AC-3 decoder required to use the
hwac3 codec.
</para>

<para>
Use the <option>-channels</option> option to select the number of output
channels.  Use <option>-channels 2</option> for a stereo downmix.  For a 4
channel downmix (Left Front, Right Front, Left Surround and Right Surround
outputs), use <option>-channels 4</option>.  In this case, any center
channel will be mixed equally to the front channels.
<option>-channels 6</option> will output all the AC-3 channels as they are
encoded - in the order Left, Right, Left Surround, Right Surround, Center and
LFE.
</para>

<para>
The default number of output channels is 2.
</para>

<para>
To use more than 2 output channels, you will need to use OSS, and have a
sound card that supports the appropriate number of output channels via the
SNDCTL_DSP_CHANNELS ioctl.  An example of a suitable driver is emu10k1
(used by Soundblaster Live! cards) from August 2001 or newer (ALSA CVS is
also supposed to work).
</para>
</sect2>

<!-- ********** -->

<sect2 id="hwac3">
<title>Hardware AC-3 decoding</title>

<para>
You need an AC-3 capable sound card, with digital out (S/PDIF). The card's
driver must properly support the AFMT_AC3 format (C-Media does).  Connect
your AC-3 decoder to the S/PDIF output, and use the <option>-ac
hwac3</option> option. It is experimental but known to work with C-Media
cards and Soundblaster Live! + ALSA (but not OSS) drivers and DXR3/Hollywood+
MPEG decoder cards.
</para>
</sect2>

<!-- ********** -->

<sect2 id="hwmpa">
<title>Hardware MPEG audio codec</title>

<para>
This codec (selected by <option>-ac hwmpa</option>) passes through MPEG audio
packets to hardware decoders, such as the ones found in full-featured DVB cards 
and DXR2 adapters.
Don't use it in combination with any other audio output device
(such as OSS and ALSA) that isn't able to decode it (you will hear
only white noise).
</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>
